<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The loyall convert, (according to the Oxford copy.) A convert will be loyall: or, some short annotations on this book; / by W. Bridges. Published by authority.</title>
            <author>Bridges, W., fl. 1644.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77378</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4483B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E257_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210047</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868881</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868881</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159220</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77378)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159220)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 44:E257[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The loyall convert, (according to the Oxford copy.) A convert will be loyall: or, some short annotations on this book; / by W. Bridges. Published by authority.</title>
                  <author>Bridges, W., fl. 1644.</author>
                  <author>Quarles, Francis, 1592-1644. Loyall convert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edward Husbands.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reprinting of and reply to the work by Francis Quarles.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept: 19th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Quarles, Francis, 1592-1644. --  Loyall convert --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Divine right of kings --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159220:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LOYALL CONVERT, (<hi>According to the</hi> Oxford <hi>Copy.</hi>)</p>
            <p>A Convert will be loyall: OR, Some ſhort <hi>Annotations</hi> on this Book; By W. BRIDGES.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>VIRG.</bibl>
               <p>Improbus haec tam culta novalia miles habebit? Barbarus has ſegetes?</p>
               <bibl>HOM.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Quaeris uter melius, Rex ne imperet, anne Senatus</l>
               <l>Neuter (quod ſaepe eſt) ſi ſit uterque malus.</l>
               <l>Sin ſit uterque bonus, Numero praeſtare ſenatum;</l>
               <l>Inque bonis multis plus reor eſſe boni.</l>
               <l>Difficile eſt numerum, forſan reperire bonorum,</l>
               <l>Sic facile eſt unum ſaepius eſſe malum.</l>
               <l>Et fuerit medius ſaepe inter utrumque Senatus,</l>
               <l>Sed tibi vix unquam rex mediocris erit.</l>
               <l>Conſilioque malus regitur meliore ſenator,</l>
               <l>Rex conſultores ſed regit ipſe ſuos:</l>
               <l>Alter ut eligitur populo; ſic naſcitur alter</l>
               <l>Sors hic caeca regit, certum ibi conſilium.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Reader, if thou wouldeſt read any more ſuch Poetry as this, See <hi>Thom. Morus Anglus,</hi> where there's much to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Authority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Edward Husbands.</hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:159220:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:159220:2"/>
            <head>To the Honeſt-hearted READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Here<note n="(a)" place="margin">When you have taken the Proteſtation to ſhew your ſelf any thing for the ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of hearts, then I ſhalbe perſwaded to give you ſome credit, and ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the honeſt hearted reader to think he hath to do with ſuch a wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; but ſuch gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen as you ſeeme to me to be, can take a ſolemn nationall Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and ſpit it up again, and without conſcience fall into that deſperate Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuited maxime, <hi>That no promiſe</hi> is to be held with ſuch, whom you can ſoon call heretiques or ſchiſmatiques, or any thing. <hi>The Searcher of hearts</hi> hath a controverſie with Covenant breakers. I would you did read ſuch places as <hi>Ier.</hi> 34.18.20. and would learn to applie them better then you have done any ſcripture that I can ſee in this treatiſe, and yet I deſire to ſee without prejudice.</note> proteſt before the Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of all hearts, that I have no End, either of Faction, or Relation in this enſuing Treatiſe. I am no<note n="(b)" place="margin">You do not know what you are, nor indeed doth any carnall man; He that doth not ſtand onely for the one thing, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.42. may and indeed (at ſome time or other) will fall into an any thing: Better men than you have confeſſed, that they did never think a man had need to be converted, till they themſelves were converted. But you are even the ſame that thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of your ſtampe are, that is to ſay, Sure ſervice-book men, and (the worſt of men) moderate men falſely ſo called, Lukewarmnes, neutrality, and ignorant pride with obſtinacy, ſee the wiſdom of God concluding them inſeparable, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.15.16.17.</note> Papiſt, no<note n="(c)" place="margin">Your ſectary we know what it is, viz. any one that is truly religious, a reformation and a religion at large is the thing ſuch as you love, that is to ſay, <hi>Sundayes no Sabbath;</hi> and the book of liberty put into practiſe again, Wakes, Church-ales, Ruſhbearings &amp;c. oh it was a merry world in thoſe dayes: upon which tearms I muſt ſay of your Peace, as once the Father ſaid, <hi>Vbi non hoc bellum ibi pax diabolica,</hi> Where there is not this ſtrife (namely between the better and worſe part) there's a deviliſh Peace. With this introduction, commonly, theſe men begin ſuch pamphlets, and they think they prevail much upon the readers affe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion, I ſay to the honeſt hearted reader, look about thee <hi>In nomine Domini incipit omne malum:</hi> Satan can transform himſelf into an Angel of light, and ſo do his Miniſters alſo, If thou eſpieſt this Proteſtation before, the ſound of his maſters heels are behind him; And he is a ſtone-cold formaliſt, ſome Chriſmas— zelot, as full of obſtinacy, as an egge is of meat, one that will tell you he would be reſolv'd, but hee's reſolv'd aforehand; of ſuch a one let Solomon give the true character, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.16. The ſluggard is wiſer in his own conceit then ſeaven men that can render a reaſon.</note> Sectarie, but a true Lover of Reformation and Peace: My Pen declines all<note n="(d)" place="margin">That we ſhall leave to the judicious reader, if there be not exceeding much of both bitterneſſe and deceit too <hi>judicent impartiales,</hi> good reader have thine eies about thee, and ſee without prejudice.</note> bitterneſſe of Spirit; all deceitfulneſſe of heart; and I may ſafely, in this particular, with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> ſay, <hi>I ſpeak the truth in Chriſt and lye not, my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence bearing me witneſſe in the holy Ghoſt, that I neither walk nor write in craftineſſe, nor handle the holy Scriptures deceitfully:</hi> Therefore if thy Cauſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:159220:3"/> be<note n="(e)" place="margin">Our cauſe is the cauſe of Ieſus Chriſt, as hath been clearly and plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully proved, nor ever yet gainſaid, but by ſophiſmes, lyes and quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. And that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive warre the Parliament hath now a foot, hath been ſufficiently vindicated, as is to ſee in the ſeverall treatiſes to that purpoſe, if we had to do with reaſonable men; Wherein (good reader) thou haſt the queſtion rightly ſtated without any <hi>Anda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batiſme,</hi> which this Gentleman hath not either ſo much wit or ſo much honeſty to do: We deſire him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to take the good counſell that he gives, And in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, laying aſide all willfull igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, pride, prejudice, private intereſts, and uncharitable cenſures, to deal ſeriouſly, and not ſo deceitfully with a truth of God. Reader, he knowes our queſtion is not what he here ſayes it to be, for all his ſpecious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. We will therefore in theſe Annotations (Chriſt willing) ſearch his ſeverall ſcriptures, and where they open, (God and thou be judge, Reader) we will not ſeek to ſhut: We deſire to conſult not only with reaſon, but with religion too, Which (in the power of it) ſuch men are ſadly ignorant of; And then to his laſt clauſe, Let truth proſper though we periſh, and God be glorified though in our confuſion; We ſay, Amen, and So be it.</note> Ieſus Chriſt, in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, I adjure thee to lay aſide all wilfull ignorance, all prejudice, all private re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spests and Intereſts, and all uncharitable cenſures: Deal faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully with thy Soul, and ſuffer wholſome admonitions: Search the ſeverall Scriptures herein contained, and where they open a Gate, climbe not thou over a Stile, Conſult with Reaſon here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in exerciz'd, and where it finds a mouth, find thou an eare: And let Truth prosper, though thou periſh; and let God be glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, although in thy Confuſion.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:159220:3"/>
            <head>THE LOYALL CONVERT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> that hath for many Ages continued the happieſt <hi>Nation</hi> on the habitable earth, enjoying the higheſt bleſſings that heaven can give, or earth receive; the fruition of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which ſetled a firme Peace; which <hi>Peace</hi> occaſion'd a full <hi>Plenty,</hi> under the gracious Government of wiſe and famous <hi>Princes,</hi> over a thriving and well-contented <hi>People,</hi> inſomuch that ſhe became the Earths <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> and the Worlds <hi>Wonder,</hi> is now the Nurcery of all <hi>Sects;</hi> her <hi>Peace</hi> is violated, her <hi>Plenty</hi> waſting, her <hi>Government</hi> diſtempered, her <hi>People</hi> diſcontented, and unnaturally embroyl'd in her own <hi>Blood,</hi> not knowing the way,<note n="(a)" place="margin">If you ſpeak for your ſelfe, Sir, you are no good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; if for us, you are no good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, all our practiſes of mercy have ſhewed, and all our prayers for mercy to God and man too, do ſhew this to be moſt falſe, we doe affect the meanes, all the lawfull meanes of peace, but our miſery is that when we ſpeake to men thereof, they make them ready to battell; <hi>The language</hi> of this Proemo is neat, but very Ieſuiticall and dangerous; Take heed (good Reader) we live in the times now, that even the Ieſuites be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to plead for the taking of the Oathes of Supremacy and Alleagiance. See the ſafeguard from ſhipwracke for a prudent Catholicke, with Doctor <hi>Featlies</hi> Annotations thereupon publiſhed by order. Sure our Church is either altered, or the Popes ſtomack that he can now digeſt us; But here it is (Reader give it thine obſervation) when there is hope that Kings will preſerve Popery, then Popery it ſelfe will ſweare to preſerve them.</note> 
               <hi>nor affecting the means</hi> of <hi>Peace;</hi> inſomuch, that ſhe is now become the <hi>By-word</hi> of the Earth, and the <hi>ſcorne</hi> of Nations.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cauſe</hi> and ground of theſe our Nationall Combuſtions, are theſe, our nationall <hi>Tranſgreſſions,</hi> which unnaturally ſprung from the neglect of that <hi>Truth</hi> we once had, and from the abuſe of that <hi>Peace</hi> we now want: Which, taking occaſion of ſome differences betwixt His <hi>Majeſtie</hi> and his two Houſes of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> hath divided our <hi>Kingdom</hi> within it ſelf, which had ſo divided it ſelf from that <hi>God,</hi> who bleſt it with ſo firme a <hi>Truth,</hi> ſo ſetled a <hi>Peace,</hi> and ſo ſweet an <hi>Unitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As that <hi>ſinne</hi> brought this <hi>diviſion,</hi> ſo this diviſion (ſharpned with mutuall Iealouſies) brought in the <hi>Sword.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:159220:4"/>
            <p>When the <hi>Lyon</hi> roars who trembles not? And when <hi>Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> thunder, who is not troubled?</p>
            <p>Among the reſt, I (who brought ſome Faggots to this <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtion</hi>) ſtood aſtoniſht, and amazed; to whom the <hi>miſchiefe</hi> was farre more manifeſt then the <hi>Remedy:</hi> At laſt, I laid my hand upon my heart, and concluded, <hi>It was the hand of God:</hi> Where being plundered in my underſtanding, I began to make a ſcrutiny, where the firſt <hi>Breach</hi> was made, that let in all theſe <hi>Miſeries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I found the whole Kingdom now contracted into a <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which conſiſted of three Eſtates; A <hi>King,</hi> a Houſe of <hi>Peeres,</hi> and a Houſe of <hi>Commons;</hi> by the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Vnity</hi> whereof, all things conducible to the <hi>Weale-publique</hi> were to be adviſed upon, preſented, and eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>I found this <hi>Vnitie</hi> diſ-joynted, and growne to variance even to <hi>Blood.</hi> The <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Adherents</hi> on the one party; and his two <hi>Houſes</hi> and their <hi>Adherents</hi> on the other.</p>
            <p>The <hi>pretence</hi> of this diviſion, was the true <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> which both proteſted to maintain; <hi>The Liberty of the Subject,</hi> which both proteſted to preſerve; <hi>the priviledges of Parliament,</hi> which both promiſe to protect: Yet nevertheſſe,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Sure this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman thinks that any thing will be granted him: I am confident, and in this I dare appeale to God and all good men, that <hi>England</hi> never ſaw her Religion and Ordinances in that glory of luſtre, as they have beene ſince this Parliament began; Such a ſpirit of prayer and preaching is gone out amongſt us, as is indeed wonderfull. But that which you call Religion's prophanation, is in deed and truth Religion's purging and reformation, <hi>viz.</hi> to plucke downe idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous croſſes, to ſilence Organs, to aboliſh relickes of Popery, to ſcum off the filth of our Liturgies and Church-ſervice, and to put away out of our <hi>Cathedrals,</hi> thoſe bawling Boyes, and drunken ſinging men; This is the prophanation of Religion we are guilty of in ſuch mens opinions as this is. True it is, in theſe ſad times of ours, and exceeding full of diſtraction, Sectaries creep in and increaſe abundantly whoſe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing (in their and the Lords due time) we doe not doubt but the great Reformer will bleſſe us with. This you can remember, &amp; object againſt our ſide; But your open Maſſes on your ſide I hear no complaint of, not a word of your <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels now, <hi>Cum privilegio,</hi> in the land here; Accidentall prophanations, (in ſuch a time as this) will happen, it cannot otherwiſe be, but voluntary and deſperate ones; volent and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent prophanations your ſide is guilty of; you authoriſe, defend, ſight for (or at leaſt with) profeſſed prophaners; yea, profeſſed enemies of Religion; yea, all Religion which hath any power or piety joyned thereunto. This writer, which, (in this ſtraine of wit) deſires to ſtrike through the ſides of our Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and profeſſion too at one blow, dares not here undertake to inſtance any one peece of the prophanation of our Religion (juſtifiedly) publiſhed, preached or practiſed in this diſtracted ſtrait of time by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Parliament, Religion, Liberty, Priviledge, and all is troden under foot by that ſide, to which this Gentleman is now a loyall Convert, as is ſeen daily, but what impudence dare averre that we doe any ſuch thing? Good Reader doe not be beguiled, but hear what this man ſaith, Religion, Liberty, Priviledge, never more prophaned, interrupted, violated, but by whom? let him ſpeake out and tell thee, or doe thou open thine eyes, and tell thy ſelfe, rather, and then thou wilt tell me, that the Gentleman hath in this, but throwne dirt in his owne ſides face.</note> the <hi>firſt</hi> never more profaned; the <hi>ſecond</hi> never more interrupted; the <hi>third</hi> never more violated.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:159220:4"/>
            <p>Standing amazed at this <hi>Riddle,</hi> I turned mine eyes upon his <hi>Majeſty;</hi> and there I viewed the <hi>Lords Annoynted,</hi> ſworn to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the eſtabliſhed <hi>Lawes</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom:</hi> I turned mine eyes upon the two <hi>Houſes;</hi> and in them I beheld the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of my Countrey, ſworne to obey his <hi>Majeſty</hi> as their ſupreme <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I heard a <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> cryed from the two <hi>Houſes:</hi> I read it; I approved it; I inclined unto it: A <hi>Declaration</hi> from his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty;</hi> I read it; I applauded it; I adhered to the juſtneſſe of it: The Parliaments <hi>Anſwer;</hi> I turned to the <hi>Parliament:</hi> His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties <hi>Reply;</hi> I returned to his <hi>Majeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus toſt and turned as a <hi>Weathercock</hi> to my own wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſſe, I reſolved it impoſſible to ſerve two <hi>Maſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I fled to <hi>Reaſon;</hi> Reaſon could not ſatisfie me: I fled to <hi>Policy,</hi> Policie could not reſolve me: at length, finding no <hi>Counſellour,</hi> but that which firſt I ſhould have ſought; I hyed me to the <hi>Book of God</hi> as the <hi>Great Oracle,</hi> and uſhering my Inqueſt with <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Humiliation,</hi> I opened the ſacred leaves, which (not by chance) preſented to my firſt eye the 20 of the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> ver. 2. <hi>The fear of a King is as the roaring of a Lyon, and who ſo provoketh him to Anger, ſinneth againſt his own ſoul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I began to ſearch, and found as many<note n="(c)" place="margin">And was there ever any pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilent hereſie in Gods Church tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> had not numerous quotations of holy Scripture? <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> obſerves it ſweetly, that He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies and perverſe opinions, inſnaring the ſoules, they are not vented, but when the good Scriptures are not well underſtood, &amp; then that which men underſtand wrongly, they aſſert to others as raſhly; See <hi>Aug. tract. in Jo.</hi> 10. It may be this Gentleman would be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to doe to me as he did to <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> or as that other <hi>Zidkijah</hi> did to <hi>Micaiah,</hi> for he ſmote him on the cheeke and ſaid, When went the ſpirit of the Lord from mee to ſpeake to thee? 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.24. For indeed ſome men thinke that none are in the favour of God ſo as they, and that God hath given to none his graces in that meaſure that they, though Chriſt knows they never knew what belonged to any ſaving grace or knowledg; but Sir, I muſt needs tell you, you have made <hi>Auguſtines</hi> words true. And ſuch as you veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7. they would be Doctors of the Law, and yet underſtand not what they ſpeak, neither whereof they affirme.</note> places to that purpoſe as would ſwell this Sheet into a <hi>Volume;</hi> ſo that in a very ſhort ſpace, I was ſo furniſhed with ſuch ſtrict <hi>Precepts,</hi> backt with ſuch ſtrong <hi>Examples,</hi> that my <hi>Iudgment</hi> was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned, and my wavering <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſo throughly convinced, that by the Grace of that <hi>Power</hi> which directed me, neither <hi>fear,</hi> nor any <hi>By-reſpects</hi> ſhall ever hereafter remove me, unleſſe ſome <hi>clearer</hi> light direct me.</p>
            <p>But, above all the Reſt, a <hi>Precept</hi> and an <hi>Example</hi> out of the Old <hi>Teſtament</hi> (ſtrongly confirmed by a <hi>Precept</hi> and an <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> out of the <hi>New</hi>) ſetled my opinion and eſtabliſhed my <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:159220:5"/>
            <p>
               <label>Pre. 1.</label>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <p>I could not have th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ught that a Royaliſt, and one of ſo tender a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as this Gentleman would ſeeme to be, would have quoted a text of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 with ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 And ſo ſtrangly derogatory to that which hee ſeemes to be ſo earneſt for. For good Reader doe but mark well: It pleaſeth God to owne (ſaith he) <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> for his ſervant, we grant it, but to do what? amongſt other things, 1 To conquer that which is none of his. 2 To be a ſcourge to the people of God. 3 To deſtroy others a while, till at length others deſtroy him; Thus God may, and doth owne the Devill for his ſervant for ſuch ſervices as theſe. Sir, you will have ſmall thanks at Court for ſuch parallels and compariſons as theſe, we hope and pray yet, that God hath appointed our gracious Soveraigne. 1 To preſerve our right and yours. 2 To be a nurſing father to Gods people. 3 To helpe to ſave them, which Ile aſſure you, Sir, will venture their deereſt bloods to ſave him: you doe exceeding ill, ſir, and I muſt tell you, it is an unreverent and unbeſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming compariſon. But let us ſee what this Scripture containes. 1 That to God belongeth the Kingdome, Rule and Government of the whole world. 2 He doth give the rule thereof even to the Beaſt of the field, to whomſoever pleaſeth him. 3 That he hath leſſe reaſon then a beaſt, which doth not ſubmit. 1 To ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the puniſhment of his iniquity, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.41. 2 And to ſeeke a place of hiding there, where God will ſecure him. For 2 great reaſons are given hereof, 1 Secret from the purpoſe of God and his decree, <hi>I have given, &amp;c. v.</hi> 6. 2 From the ſinne of man which God doth intend hereby to ſcourge for a time, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o the Lord tels them plainly, <hi>verſe</hi> 7. And therefore whoſoever ſhall dare to ſtrive or reſiſt, muſt now know it is no leſſe then a diſobedience and God-reſiſtance. <hi>The ſumme.</hi> Your Land (O ye Iewes) heretofore yours (while ye were mine) and governed by your owne King, I have now given away unto a ſtrange King, even the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the government ſhall be his over you all, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and what yours is, to the beaſt of the field. Now your wiſdome will be to ſubmit to me and him; yea, to me in him that you may ſhevv your paſſive obedience, if otherwiſe two miſchiefes will enſue againſt you, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 Severe puniſhments, ſword, famine, &amp;c. 2 And that untill they be wholy given into his hands, hereupon a double exhortation is given. 1 Do not heare (expreſſed). 2 Much leſſe beleeve (implyed) thoſe that ſay, Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall not ſerve the King of <hi>Babel,</hi> and a binding reaſon, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. <hi>For they prophecie a lie, &amp;c.</hi> Laſtly, the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and promiſe, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. But now what doth this Text conclude. 1 Hath God given away our Land and King to a forrainer? Who ſent you to preach this doctrine? 2 They are commanded by God to this which is not our caſe. 3 Thus you argue, The people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> muſt not refuſe the meanes of their ſafety, how unlikely ſoever. Therefore the people of <hi>England</hi> muſt not refuſe the meanes of their ſlavery how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull ſoever. Its very well argued, ſir, indeed. But honeſt Reader marke a little and ſee what the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man would conclude hence. 1 Our King is as that King of <hi>Babel,</hi> whom God hath appointed to do what he will. 2 Our Parliament the people that will not obey, therefore deſigned to fire, ſword, &amp;c. 3 All the holy learned of the Land are dreamers, enchanters, ſorcerers, and men that prophecy a lie unto you. 4 Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Countrimen put your necks under the yoak of the King, and you ſhall remain ſtill in your land, occupy and dwell therein; yes marry ſhall you and weare wooden ſhooes, as the Peſants do in <hi>France:</hi> Reader I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to thy ſoule, is not here peſtilent perverting Gods truth? Do not ſuch men torment and ſet on the rack (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) Gods truth, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. This is the firſt Precept with which this good man was ſo ſatisfied.</p>
               </note> The firſt <hi>Precept</hi> out of the Old, <hi>Ier.</hi> 27.6. where it pleaſed <hi>God</hi> to own <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> his ſervant, (although a known <hi>Pagan,</hi> a profeſt <hi>Idolater,</hi> and a <hi>fierce Perſecuter</hi> of all Gods Children) concerning whom he ſaith, v. 8. <hi>They that ſerve not the King of Babylon, and that will not put their necks un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Yoak, I will puniſh them with the ſword, Famine, and the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, till I have conſumed them.</hi> v. 9. <hi>Therefore hearken not to your Diviners and Prophets, that ſay unto you, You ſhall not ſerve the King of Babylon, for they propheſie a lye unto you,</hi> v. 10. <hi>But the nations that ſhall ſerve the King of Babylon, and bring their necks under his Yoak, thoſe will I let remain in their own land, (ſaith the Lord) and they ſhall till it, and dwell therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can there be a ſtricter <hi>Precept?</hi> or could there be a more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious <hi>Prince?</hi> And yet this <hi>Precept,</hi> and yet this <hi>Prince</hi> muſt be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:159220:5"/> obeyed: nay, <hi>ſub poena</hi> too; Upon the pain of Gods high wrath, fully expreſt in <hi>Famine, Sword</hi> and <hi>Peſtilence,</hi> not only upon the <hi>People,</hi> but upon the <hi>Prieſts</hi> alſo, that ſhall perſwade them unto <hi>diſobedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">The 2 Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept is the old place <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3. &amp;c. To this I anſwer that this Gentleman ſure doth ſuppoſe that that he can ſay more then Doctor <hi>Fern,</hi> or elſe he would never preſſe it ſo farre; But I will not dare to ſuppoſe that I can ſay more than they, which have given him anſwer. Let the reader apply himſelf unto Maſter <hi>Burroughes</hi> in the end of the treatiſe, intituled. <hi>The Lord of hoſts:</hi> and oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs abouring excellently up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that ſubject. Only thus much give me leave to advertiſe: The Gentleman doth firſt hoodwinck you and then abuſe you. 1. Gods command his reaſon, and that under, thereat, they are altogether, yea and every one by himſelf, that which we deſire to tremble to think of diſobedienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to; For they are ſuch a three fold coard as cannot be broken, but we break with them. 2 Equality with our ſoveraign, ſuperiority, or ſupremacy over him, let this book object againſt them that are guilty of deſiring ſuch a thing, We utterly diſclaim and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the thought therof, And therefore herein the author fights with his ſhadow, and not with us. 3 His diſtinction of active and paſſive obedience, power, praiſe, pliance, prayers, &amp;c. Suppoſe all this ſhould be admitted, yet the author hits not the queſtion, alas he comes not neer the mark. Indeed no more they do any of them by their good will. 4 The paral<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll too between the two Scriptures that is to ſay, between the 13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1, 2, 3, and 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 11.29. with that flaſh of wit diſcerning the Lords body, and diſcerning the Lords annointed, that he ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of ordinance, and the puniſhment of diſobedience &amp;c, allow him all this, And all this is beſide the buſineſſe in hand and hath nothing in it but froth: How eaſily and with no noiſe falls all this Babel to pieces thus. 1 He that rebells againſt Gods commandement, ſhall receive to himſelf judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, True, but we do not ſo, therefore, &amp;c. 2 He that deſires to be equall with, or above his King, he &amp;c. But we abhorre it with our hearts: therefore &amp;c. and ſo of all the reſt, This ſpiders web is ſoon ſwept down you ſee, Much reading, I know by my ſelf, is a weariſomneſſe to the fleſh; And though there be many books yet every one hath not time to read them, obſerve therefore, good Reader, without prejudice theſe following things in anſwer to this precept. 1 Obe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ience to the King may be denied, not only in things unlawfull by the Law of God, but man alſo; This is granted by the Kings ſide, this poſition, <hi>That Gods Law and man's Law do limit Kings power.</hi> 2 Reſiſtance is lawfull with theſe three cautions: 1 If there be the conſent of the two houſes of Parliament. 2 If that reſiſtance be defenſive. 3 If the King be bent to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw all religion, Lawes, Libertyes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſhew nothing but will: For you know, ſir, and for ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me do not diſſemble it, that <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> old rule is, He that Governs by Law is a King, by luſt is a tyrant. The next book therefore that this Gentleman writes, we ſhall intreat him to ſatisfy the reader in thoſe particulars above and ſuch as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe below, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 What is the difference between <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> power and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrength for ſurely this muſt be regarded. 2 There is difference between theſe two He hath, and He is, the greateſt power, let it be ſpoken of whom it will. 3 The reſiſtance of the Power, and the reſiſtance of the will are things different. 4 Theſe concurrences in a Governour, which all have graunted. 1 The power, which is from God. 2 Perſon, which is from men. 3 Qualification, which is from himſelf. 4 Limitation, which is from the Law divine and humane. 5 Let him alſo ſatisfy us in theſe two things more, that is to ſay. 1 Though duty, breach of oath and covenant doth not make forfeyture of power, yet whether any breach doth ſo. 2 Wheth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r power given to King, Parliament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may be reaſſumed? when, how, in what caſes, and by whom? The light of reaſon we have, hath taught us this, and we cannot forget it, That ſpirituall good things have ſuch means to preſerve them, Which is a truth warranted by Gods word. That naturall and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill good things muſt ſurely have means to preſerve them alſo, Such therefore would I intreate the next diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of this Gentlemans to be, as may give ſatisfaction in theſe things, or elſe he does nothing to the purpoſe.</note>
               <label>2 Pre.</label> The ſecond <hi>Precept</hi> is enjoyned us out of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> Ro. 13.1. <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher Powers, for there is no power but of God; the Powers that be, are ordained of God: whoſoever therefore reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves damnation.</hi> This <hi>Power,</hi> (this <hi>King</hi>) to whom S. <hi>Paul</hi> commandeth this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, was <hi>Nero,</hi> the bloody perſecutor of all that honoured the bleſſed Name of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:159220:6"/>
            <p>Gods <hi>Command</hi> ſhould be a ſufficient Argument, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is enough: But when he adds a <hi>Reaſon</hi> too, he anſwers all <hi>Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</hi> But when he threatens a <hi>puniſhment</hi> (no leſſe then <hi>damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>) upon the reſiſtance thereof, he hath uſed all means to perſwade a <hi>neceſsity</hi> of obedience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not equall, much leſſe ſuperiour. And what is taking up of <hi>Armes,</hi> but an implyed ſuppoſition of at leaſt <hi>equality?</hi> What are the hopes of conqueſt but an Ambition of <hi>Superiority?</hi> What is condemning, judging, or depoſing, but <hi>Supremacy?</hi> For it is againſt the <hi>nature</hi> of an Inferiour to condemne, judge, or depoſe a Superiour.</p>
            <p>And, leſt the Rebellious ſhould confine his obedience to a <hi>good Prince,</hi> the next words reply,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For there is no power but of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Power in it ſelf is neither good nor evill, but as it is in <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecto,</hi> the perſon; If an evill King, an evill Power, If a good King, a good Power: God ſends the one in Mercy; and we muſt be ſubject; the other in Judgment, and we muſt be ſubject: in things lawfull, <hi>actively;</hi> in things unlawfull, <hi>paſſively:</hi> If a good King, he muſt have our <hi>praiſe</hi> and our <hi>plyance;</hi> If an evill King, he muſt have our <hi>Prayers,</hi> and our <hi>Patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that reſiſteth the Power</hi> (whether good or evill, for all pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is of God) <hi>reſiſts an Ordinance of God</hi> (Ordinances of men are not reſiſted without ruine) <hi>and whoſoever reſiſteth, ſhall receive,</hi> but what? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>damnation to themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, compare this place with that 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29. <hi>He that ſhall eat this Bread, and drink this cup of the Lord unworthily, eateth and drinketh,</hi> What? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>damnation</hi> to himſelf. If then there be proportion betwixt the <hi>Sin</hi> and the <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> you may hereby gather the heinouſneſſe of <hi>diſobedience,</hi> the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof is the very ſame with his, that is guilty of the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and blood of our Lord;</hi> to the one, <hi>for not diſcerning the Lords Body,</hi> to the other, <hi>for not diſcerning the Lords Annoynted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> The Lords <hi>Annoynted?</hi> And who is he? None but the <hi>regenerate:</hi> Chriſt is not Chriſt to any, to whom Ieſus is not Ieſus.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> Gods Word anſwers your ſilly Objection, not I: was not <hi>Saul</hi> Gods Annoynted 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.9. Was not <hi>Cyrus</hi> Gods
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:159220:6"/> Annoynted, and many more whom <hi>God</hi> acknowledges ſo, and yet wicked Kings?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cyrus is mine Annointed yet he hath not known me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Example. 1.</label>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">For the firſt Example; Truely I do but deſire to appeal to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is ſound and without prejudice, not Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizing the name of King, Court, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as not long ſince we were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to do ſomething elſe. And by thoſe which now deſire to preach us as deep into the blind obedience, as ever they did. I have (I thank God) three rules fitted to that threefold obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which have not yet failed me in the truſt I have committed to them; I am infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that,
<list>
                     <item>1 Blind obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence wanteth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion.</item>
                     <item>2 Implicite ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience wanteth truth.</item>
                     <item>3 Seditious and ſervile obedience want's juſtice.</item>
                  </list> Reader, do but obſerve with what obedience they would have thee obey, and alſo take the good memorandum, given thee by an Ancient, And be not blindly obſtinate, and Ile deſire no more, <hi>Tertullian's</hi> cenſure of the people of his time is thus <hi>Majore formidine Ceſarem obſervatis; quam ipſumde Olympo Iovem;</hi> which is in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh thus in effect, I would to God ſome of you would learn to fear God a little, which pretend you fear (and love the King ſo much) and I could like it well; <hi>Michior Canus</hi> takes occaſion to ſay of the <hi>Italians</hi> theſe words, <hi>Vos Itali vultis deum habere in pane, quem non creditis eſſe in caelis, in</hi> Engliſh, You <hi>Italians</hi> will needs have God to be in the bread in the Sacrament, which I'm afraid you hardly beleeve to be in heaven. <hi>ſic ilic in vita. Melanct.</hi> But to the point, this firſt Example Reader, I judge it (to this buſineſſe) very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congruent and abſurd: Abſurd I ſay, For do but obſerve, and the force of the reaſonning lyes thus. 1 Three children captives do yeild paſſive obedience to the lawfull commands of a free Monarch in a ſtrange land. Therefore all freemen ought to yeild paſſive obedience without reſiſtance to the meer will of a mixt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, (the Parliament then ſitting and diſſenting thereto) in their owne land I ſhall pray the Reader to obſerve well the agreement between this caſe and ours. 2 It is not lawfull in any caſe to reſiſt (no though the commands be altogether unlawfull) a King that is to Govern by will. Therefore unlawfull alſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt him (or his bad Councell which is to Govern by Law; Thus the Gentleman argues from the firſt of thoſe Examples which did ſo confirm him.</note> The firſt Example for our Obedience the Old Teſtament propoſeth to our imitation, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar</hi> the King of Babylon ſets up a golden Image, <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> were commanded to fall down and worſhip it.</p>
            <p>The King a known Pagan commands groſſe Idolatry, did theſe men conſpire? Or (being Rulers of the Province of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel) did they invite the Jewes into a Rebellion? did theſe, to ſtrengthen their own Faction, blaſt their Soveraigns Name with Tyranny and Paganiſme? Did they endevour by ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals and impious Aſperſions to render him odious to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? Did they encourage their Provinces to take up Arms for the defence of their Liberties or Religion? Did they ſeize upon or ſtop his Revenues? or annihilate his Power? did they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrange themſelves from his Preſence? Murther his Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, or would they have ſlighted his gracious Offers? No, being called by their Prince, they came; and being comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to give actuall obedience to his unlawfull commands, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the modeſtie of their firſt anſwer, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.19. <hi>We are not carefull to anſwer thee in this matter;</hi> and being urged, marke their pious Reſolution in the ſecond: <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Be it knowne, O King, we will not ſerve thy gods, nor worſhip the golden Image which thou haſt ſet up.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:159220:7"/>
            <p>The King threatens the Furnace, they yeeld their bodies to the Furnace, and ſay, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.17. <hi>God whom we ſerve will deliver us out of thy hands,</hi> and is not, he will deliver <hi>Thee into our hands.</hi> They expect deliverance rather in their paſſive obedience, then in their actuall reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> But they were few in number, and their forces not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> Admit that which all Hiſtories deny, Was not God as able to ſubdue <hi>Him</hi> with ſo few, as to deliver them from ſo many? Had their weakneſſe leſſe reaſon (for the cauſe of Gods apparent diſhonour) to expect a miraculous aſſiſtance in thoſe dayes of frequent Miracles, then we after ſo long a ceſſation of Miracles? Gods glory will not be vindicated by unlawfull meanes, or unwarrantable proceedings.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Obj.</label> I, but we take up Armes, not againſt the King, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his evill Counſellors.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> Adherents ye meane, A rare diſtinction! And, tell me; whoſe power have his Adherents? The Kings; By which appeares, ye take up Arms againſt the Kings power; <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8. <hi>He that reſiſteth the power</hi> (it is not ſaid the Prince) <hi>ſhall receive dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> Again, <hi>Where the word of a King is, there is power.</hi> God joyned the King and his power, and who dare ſeparate them? They that take up Armes againſt the Parliaments power (you ſay) take up Armes againſt the Parliament; do not they then that take up Armes againſt the Kings power, by the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, take up Armes againſt the King? Now looke back upon your intricate diſtinction, and bluſh.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Obj.</label> But, if the King betray the <hi>Truſt</hi> repoſed in him by his Subjects they may ſuſpend their obedience, and reſiſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">You and ſuch as you the Kings flatterers; and it is pitty to ſee what daubing here is with untempered mortar.</note> Kings are Gods Vicegerents and cannot be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to give an account to any, but to God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.4. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, againſt thee only have I ſinned:</hi> That is to thee, to thee onely muſt I give an account. Though I have ſinned againſt <hi>Uriah,</hi> by my <hi>Act;</hi> and againſt my people by my Example, yet againſt Thee have I onely ſinned. You cannot deprive, or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them in what you never gave them. God gave them their Power, and who art thou that dareſt reſiſt it? <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.15. <hi>By me Kings raign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Obj.</label> But, his <hi>Crown</hi> was ſet upon his Head by his Subjects, upon ſuch and ſuch conditions.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:159220:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Why was the penalty upon the ſaile not expreſſed then? Coronation is but a humane Ceremony, And was he not Proclaimed before he was Crowned? Proclaimed? But what? A King? And did not you at the ſame inſtant by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative conſequence, proclaime your ſelves Subjects? And ſhall Subjects condition with their King,<note n="(h)" place="margin">He is bound by the law to the law, which is the common Sponſor between him and the ſubject, <hi>viz.</hi> that the ſubject ſhall pay tribute give obedience, &amp;c and then, that he ſhall enjoy his protection too, or elſe he is in an ill caſe.</note> or will Kings bind themſelves to their Subjects, upon the forfeiture of their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, after they have received their Regall Authority?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> But the King hath, by Writ, given his power to his Parliament, and therefore what they do, they do by vertue of his Power.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> The King, by his writ, gives not away his power, but communicates it. By the vertue of which Writ, they are called <hi>ad tractandum &amp; conſulendum de arduis Regni,</hi> to treat and adviſe concerning the difficulties of the Kingdom: Here is all the power<note n="(i)" place="margin">Yes to enact ſomething too ſurely, Sir, you have forgot your ſelf: but if Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents be found out, and reſcued from the hand of juſtice, what then? Nay if they be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med againſt them which ſhould do juſtice on them, what then?</note> the Writ gives them, and where they exceed, they uſurp the Kings power, being both againſt the Law of God, and the conſtitutions of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> Well, but in caſe of neceſſitie, when Religion and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty lye at the ſtake, the Conſtitutions of the Kingdom (for the preſervation of the Kingdom) may ſuffer a Diſpenſation.<note n="(k)" place="margin">Here's no law of God broken yet, unleſſe you ſhew us more.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> Admit that: But what neceſſity may diſpenſe with the violation of the Law of God? the deviation where from is evill, and, Thou ſhalt do no evill that good may come thereon.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> But, we take not Armes againſt the King, but only to bring Delinquents to condigne puniſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> And, who are they? even thoſe that take up Armes for the King; which an unrepealed Statute, 11. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. acquits. But, admit Statutes may be broken, and you ſeek to puniſh them; Who gave you the power ſo to do? The Law: And what Law denyes the King power to pardon Delinquents? God that hath put power into the hand of Majeſty, hath likewiſe planted mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in the heart of Soveraignty: And, will ye take away both his birth-right and his Bleſſing alſo? Take heed, you do not ſlight that, which one day may prove your<note n="(l)" place="margin">Our reioycing is the teſtimony of our conſcience, that we ſhall have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with the King of Kings, which is our ſoul's ſole ſanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary. In the mean time you reaſon well, The King may pardon ſome Delinquents, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don any; yea all. A King hath mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy for D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>linquents therefore, let him ſpare them, nay arme them againſt thoſe that indevour to do their duties in ridding the common wealth or Church of them.</note> Sanctuary.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> But, the King, being a Mixt Monarch, is bound to his own Lawes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> There be two ſorts of Lawes, directive and coercive: As to the firſt, he is only bound to make his accompt to God; ſo to the ſecond, he is only lyable to the hand of God: who
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:159220:8"/> ſhall ſay unto him, what doſt thou?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> But Kings now adayes have not ſo abſolute a power, as the Kings mentioned in the Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> Who limited it? God or man? Man<note n="(m)" place="margin">See before confeſſed that, the Kings power is limited by Gods law and mans law too, where's the limitation, if he may do what he will, and muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to none but God? For in vain is he petitioned, or ſubſidy, or aid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied him, For he may take all when he pleaſeth, and is to account to none but God.</note> could not limit the Power he never gave: if God, ſhew me where; till then, this objection is frivolous.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> But, when Kings and their aſſiſtance make an offenſive, and a deſtructive warre againſt their Parliament, may they not then take up defenſive Armes?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> It is no offenſive Warre for a King to endeavour the Recovery of his ſurrepted right;<note n="(n)" place="margin">Prove a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repted right, and you ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</note> however, are not the Members of a Parliament Subjects to their Soveraign? If not, who are they? If Subjects, ought they not to be ſubject? Gods people, the Iews, <hi>Heſter</hi> 8. that were to be deſtroyed by the Kings Command, neither did, not durſt make a defenſive Warre againſt his abuſed power, untill they firſt obtained the Kings Conſent.</p>
            <p>But admit it lawfull, (though neither granted nor warranted) that ſubjects may upon ſuch tearms make a defenſive Warre; does it not quite croſſe the nature of a defenſiue Warre, to Aſſayle, purſue, and diſpoſſeſſe?</p>
            <p>When you ſhot five peeces of Ordnance, before one was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned at <hi>Edge-hill,</hi> was that defenſive? When you beſieged <hi>Redding,</hi> which you after ſlighted, was that defenſive? When you affronted <hi>Baſing-houſe,</hi> was that defenſive?</p>
            <p>The warrantable weapons againſt an angry King, are Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, Diſwaſion, wiſe reproofe (by ſuch as are neareſt to him) Petition, Prayer, and Flight. All other weapons will at laſt wound them that uſe them.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(o)" place="margin">For the two Examples of our bleſſed Saviour, to it I anſwer that, This example alſo I judge to be like the former and very impertinent. My reaſon is, Our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord had an aime only at the buſineſſe which he came to do, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 To do the work of his miniſtery <hi>Eſa.</hi> 61.1, 2. And 2 in due time to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the death on the croſſe, upon which 2 of the parts of his office were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant, <hi>viz.</hi> the propheticall and prieſtly office, for the 3 part, that is his Kingly.</note>
               <label>Ex. 2</label> The 2 Example was left us out of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by Him that is the true preſident of all holy obedience, our bleſſed Saviour; whoſe humility and ſufferance was ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us as a Copy for all generations to practiſe by. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>The temporall Kingdom of the Iewes, ſucceſſively uſurpt by theſe two heathen Princes, <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> and <hi>Tiberius,</hi> two Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporaries, was his naturall Birth-right, deſcended from his Type and Aunceſtor King <hi>David.</hi> Had not he as great an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in that Crown, as we have in this Common-wealth? Was not He as tender-eyed towards his own naturall people, as we to one another?</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:159220:8"/>
            <p>Was not the Truth as deare to Him, (who was the very <hi>Truth</hi>) and the way to it; as direct to Him (that was the only <hi>way</hi>) as to us?</p>
            <p>Was not <hi>He</hi> the great <hi>Reformer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had the <hi>Sword</hi> been a neceſſary ſtickler in Reformation, how happened it that he miſtook his <hi>Weapon</hi> ſo? In ſtead of a trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, he lifted up his <hi>Voice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Were <hi>Plots, Policies, Propoſitions, Prophanations, Plunderings,</hi> Militarie <hi>Preparations,</hi> his way to Reformation? were they not his own words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.52. <hi>He that taketh up the Sword ſhall periſh by the Sword.</hi> Nor was it want of <hi>ſtrength,</hi> that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed not in a Martiall way: <hi>Could not he command more then twelue legions of Angels?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or had he pleaſed to uſe the Arme of <hi>fleſh,</hi> could not he that raiſed the <hi>dead,</hi> raiſe a conſiderable <hi>Army?</hi> Sure, St. <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> would have ventured his head upon a fairer <hi>Quarell,</hi> and St. <hi>Peter</hi> drawn his ſword to a bloodier end; No queſtion, but St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the twelve <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Diſciples</hi> would have proved as tough <hi>Colonells</hi> as your aſſociated <hi>Eſſex</hi> Prieſts did <hi>Captaines;</hi> and doubtleſſe St. <hi>Peter,</hi> who converted 3000 in one day, would have raiſed a ſtrong Army in <hi>ſix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> well knew, that <hi>Caeſar</hi> came not thither without divine <hi>permiſſion;</hi> In reſpect whereof, He became obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to the very <hi>ſhaddow</hi> of a King; and whom the actively re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted not, he paſſively obeyed.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> I, but there was a <hi>neceſſity</hi> of his obedience, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, to make him <hi>capable</hi> of a ſhamefull death.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> No, his obedience, as well as death, was <hi>voluntary;</hi> which makes you guilty of a <hi>ſhamefull</hi> argument.<note n="(p)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bona verba quaeſo.</hi> you are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptorily igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, Sir, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit your diſcretion very often. The death of our Lord was <hi>voluntary quoad depoſitionem,</hi> it is true, himſelf ſaith ſo <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.18. I lay down my life, no man takes it away. But yet neceſſary too, <hi>quoad decretum:</hi> as I ſhall ſhew you out of your owne ſcriptures <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.54. how then ſhould the Scriptures be fulfilled which ſay that it muſt be ſo.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> But, He was a <hi>ſingle perſon;</hi> We, a <hi>repreſentative body:</hi> what is unexpedient in the one, is lawfull in the other</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> Worſe and worſe! If our bleſſed Saviour be not <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative,</hi> Tell me whereof art thou a <hi>Member?</hi> woe be to that Body <hi>politick,</hi> which endeavours not to be conformed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Head <hi>Myſticall.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:159220:9"/>
            <p>He preacht <hi>peace;</hi>
               <note n="(q)" place="margin">If alwayes you ſay ſomething, but if ever other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, either by himſelf or his, your paralell is not worth a point See <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.34. and be not raſh.</note> Your Martiall Miniſters (by what au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority they beſt know) proclaime warre.<note n="(r)" place="margin">He preached obedience with li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.21. Ceſar's due no more, you (like a company of flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers as you are) preach it without limitation.</note> He, <hi>Obedience;</hi> They, <hi>Sedition:</hi>
               <note n="(s)" place="margin">Do not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently tax us of preaching lies, ſhew any one ſo doing, and name him, otherwiſe you muſt needs father the lye. The Gentleman you glance at, in the word <hi>(Martiall)</hi> is quite beyond your aſperſion, and till the Court admire ſuch <hi>Micaiah's,</hi> I am afraid the Kings undertakings wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be but like <hi>Ahabs</hi> journey to <hi>Ramoth Gilead,</hi> though 400 ſuch as you ſay all, <hi>Goe up and Proſper.</hi>
               </note> He, <hi>Truth;</hi> They, <hi>Lyes:</hi> He,<note n="(t)" place="margin">Order is a word of great latitude, Sir, and I beleeve you mean, Order of Biſhops, Order of Cathedralls, Order of Church-ſervice, &amp;c. Look about you, and you have been anſwered. No, know God is the God of order, and not of confuſion.</note> 
               <hi>Order;</hi> They, <hi>Confuſion:</hi> He, <hi>Bleſſedneſſe</hi> to the peace-makers; They, courage to the<note n="(u)" place="margin">In your two laſt particulars you beg ſhamefully. 1 You would have us think ſuch as you mean to be Peacemakers, Who are indeed our only Peacebreakers. You are ſuch, and we have found you ſuch on every treaty that we have had with you, like him that ſhed the blood of warre in Peace. We have found you as the men of <hi>Meſeck</hi> and <hi>Kedar</hi> (degenerating indeed) which whiles we (and you too) talk of Peace, make you ready to battaile. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 120.7: 2 You would have us think that impriſonment for malignity, and as incendiaries in a ſtate, is perſecution for righteouſneſſe. No we know you ſuffer as evill doers, are buffetted for your faults, and deſire you to remember the old rule; <hi>Non poena ſed cauſa martyrem facit,</hi> It is not the puniſhment, but the cauſe which makes the Martyr. Sir, it becomes them that bring ſuch a rayling ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation as this, ſo full of bitterneſſe, and groſſe falſehood, to draw it to particulars, and to ſay, This and this was done by ſuch and ſuch a perſon, and perſons. We who deſire information, beleeve me, do think, the blaſphemies, lyes, and braſſe-brow'd impudencies to be on your ſide.</note> 
               <hi>Perſecutors:</hi> He, <hi>Bleſſedneſſe</hi> to the perſecuted; They brand them with <hi>Malignitie</hi> that call them bleſſed.</p>
            <p>God was not heard in the <hi>whirlewind,</hi> but in the <hi>ſtill voice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, his thoughts are not as our thoughts, neither are our wayes like his wayes.</p>
            <p>But, whence proceeds all this? even from a <hi>viperous</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration (which hath long neſted in this unhappy <hi>Iſland</hi>) and thoſe encreaſed multitudes of <hi>ſimple ſoules,</hi> ſedued by their <hi>ſeeming</hi> ſanctity, who taking advantage of our late too great <hi>abuſe</hi> of Ceremonies, are turn'd deſperate enemies to all <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> being out of charity with the very <hi>Lords prayer,</hi> becauſe it comes within the Popiſh <hi>Liturgie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How many of theſe have lately challenged the name of <hi>ſanctified</hi> Veſſells, for containing the poyſon of unnaturall <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition?</hi> How many of theſe have uſurpt the ſtile of <hi>well-affected,</hi> for diſ-affecting <hi>peace?</hi> How many of theſe have counterfeited the honour of good <hi>Patriots,</hi> for largely contributing towards the <hi>Ruines</hi> of their Country? How many does this <hi>Army</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of? How for their ſakes is <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> connived at! <hi>Sacriledge</hi> permitted! How for their encouragement, are <hi>Lyes</hi> and braſſe-brow'd <hi>Impudencies</hi> invented, nay publiſht (nay publiſhed in their very <hi>pulpits</hi>) and tolerated (if not commanded) even by <hi>them,</hi> who (perchance, where this quarrell ended) would throw
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:159220:9"/> the firſt <hi>stone</hi> at them! How many of our Learned, Religious, and Orthodox <hi>Divines</hi> (who by their able <hi>Tongues</hi> and <hi>Pens,</hi> have defended and maintained the true ancient and Catholique <hi>Faith,</hi> and vindicated the <hi>Reformed</hi> Religion from the aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of her potent Adverſaries) are now plundered in their <hi>Goods,</hi> ſequeſtred in their <hi>Livings,</hi> impriſon'd in their <hi>perſons,</hi> (if not forced in their <hi>Conſciences</hi>) whileſt their Wives and poore<note n="(x)" place="margin">
                  <p>There ſhalbe judgement merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to him that ſheweth no mercy. <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.13. I pray you open your eies, and ſee the juſtice of the Lord of hoſts in this thing. <hi>Adonibezek</hi> ſhall riſe up in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt you, his confeſſion is <hi>Iud.</hi> 1.7. As I have done, ſo God hath rewarded me. So muſt you ſay too. Remember your earecutting, undo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, depriving, ſuſpending, merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe high Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion Court, and then ſay, God is juſt.</p>
                  <p>When a ſhips la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of thoſe that your party drave to <hi>New-England</hi> were ſayling thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, O (ſayes a creature of one of your Courts) that a ſtorm would come now, and ſinke all theſe into the bottome of the ſea! this is a peece of your cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
                  <p>Beleeve it, Sir, you have been bloodily mercileſſe, and the juſt God is now in making inquiſition.</p>
               </note> Children begging their bread, are left to the mercy of theſe <hi>unmercifull</hi> times; even for the encouragement of them, whoſe<note n="(y)" place="margin">Surgunt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docti, et rapiunt cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, et nos cum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus doctrinis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris detrudimur in gehennam. Aug.</note> 
               <hi>pedantick</hi> learning durſt never ſhew her ridiculous face before an eaſie <hi>School-man,</hi> whoſe livelyhoods they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily uſurp, not diſpenſing the <hi>bread of life,</hi> but the <hi>darnell</hi> of giddy-headed <hi>fancy</hi> and <hi>ſedition,</hi> abhorring the way to peace, and maligning thoſe that enſue it.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ob.</label> I, but we deſire Peace, ſo we may have <hi>Truth</hi> too.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> What mean ye by having Truth? The preſervation of the <hi>Old</hi> Truth, or the inſtitution of a <hi>New?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If ye feare the <hi>alteration</hi> of the Old, (having your Soveraigns <hi>Oath,</hi> which you dare not beleeve) what other aſſurance can you have?</p>
            <p>The Blood you ſhed, is <hi>certain;</hi> the change you feare, is<note n="(z)" place="margin">It is an eaſie matter for you to write ſo, but it is not ſo eaſie for you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> make wiſe men think ſo. <hi>Solomons</hi> prudent man, and his fool, with their previſions, and proviſions, are to be ſeen, <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.3. You are very confident of your abiliti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, that dare oppoſe your judgement, to that of a whole State.</note> 
               <hi>uncertain:</hi> it is no wiſdom to apply a <hi>deſperate</hi> Remedy to a <hi>ſuſpected</hi> diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>If the enjoyment of peace depends upon a full <hi>aſſurance</hi> of Truth, our diſcords may bear an everlaſting Date: God hath threatned to remove his <hi>Candleſtick,</hi> and our wickedneſſe juſtly feares it; And ſo long as we feare it, ſhall we abjure <hi>peace,</hi> the bleſſed <hi>meanes</hi> to prevent it? He that ſeekes to <hi>ſettle</hi> Truth by the ſword, <hi>diſtracts</hi> it.</p>
            <p>Or is it a Truth ye <hi>want?</hi> If ſo, Is it of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> or of <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline?</hi> If of <hi>Doctrine, Actum eſt de noſtra Religione,</hi> Farewell our Religion. Or, is it of <hi>Diſcipline?</hi> Diſcipline is but a <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</hi> And did the Lord of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> diſpenſe with a <hi>morall</hi> Law, for the preſervation of an <hi>Oxes</hi> life, or an <hi>Aſſes?</hi> and ſhall we, to alter ſome few indifferent <hi>Ceremonies</hi> (allowed by the Parliaments of three <hi>pious</hi> and <hi>wiſe</hi> Princes, and the practiſe of many holy <hi>Martyrs,</hi> who ſealed the true proteſtant Religion
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:159220:10"/> with their blood) cry down Peace, and ſhed the Blood of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſand <hi>Chriſtians?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our ſeduced Proteſtants will have no <hi>ſet Forms</hi> of prayer, but what proceed immediately from their own <hi>Fancies.</hi> This is their Truth.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Semi-ſeparatiſts</hi> will hear our Sermons (if they like the Teacher) but no <hi>Divine Service.</hi> This is their Truth.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Separatiſts</hi> will not <hi>communicate</hi> in our Churches, nor <hi>joyne</hi> in our Congregations. That is their<note n="(*)" place="margin">Truth is one, as is the God of truth; And as for the Separatiſts, Anabaptiſts, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What the State thinks of them, and how it proceeds againſt ſome of them, you ſhould ſeek to know before you ſeem to cenſure. We contend not, Sir, for ſuch a truth as muſt have a touch of an <hi>Iriſh</hi> toleration. <hi>The Independants,</hi> thoſe Gentlemen do dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in judgement in that point, tis true, yet modeſtly, and without moro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity: Reckon them with reverence, Sir, I pray you, they ſhall for lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning go check by jowl, with your ſide of the firſt form, And if you take them in their Pulpit imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, beleeve me none of yours are to be compared with them; Alas, Sir, preaching, that is to ſay, opening the whole counſell of God, hath been out of faſhion at Court, ever ſince I was born; More the ſinne, and ſhame of ſome bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, And the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced <hi>Amos</hi> 7.12.16.17. Reader, obſerve if it be not accompliſhing: Neither is the quarrell for a few ceremonies, we contend for ſubſtance. For all our liberties, as we are men, and Chriſtian men, do lie now at ſtake, and we hope the Lord will diſcover himſelf to be for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is therein.</note> Truth.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> will not baptize till yeares of diſcretion, and <hi>Re-baptize.</hi> That is their Truth.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Antinomians</hi> will have no <hi>Repentance.</hi> This is their Truth.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Independants</hi> will have an univerſall <hi>Parity;</hi> This is their Truth.</p>
            <p>Good God, when ſhall we have <hi>peace,</hi> if not till all their Truthes meet!</p>
            <p>
               <label>Obj.</label> But, Chriſt ſayes, <hi>Mark.</hi> 10.34. <hi>I come not to bring Peace, but the ſword:</hi> therefore for the Propagation of Peace, it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to uſe the Sword.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> So he is tearmed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23. a <hi>ſtumbling block,</hi> and does that warrant to ſtumble? So, He ſayes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.31. <hi>All you ſhall be offended becauſe of me;</hi> and doth this Patronize our Offences? The Law is good and juſt: Becauſe <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7. <hi>then we had not knowne ſin but by the Law.</hi> Is it therefore lawfull for us to ſinne? God forbid.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour brings the Sword among us, as wholſom meat brings ſickneſſe to a weakly ſick ſtomack, or Phyſick to a body abounding with Humors; not intentionally, but occaſionally.</p>
            <p>Thus, by your erroneous and weake miſtakes, you make the Prince of Peace the Patron of your unnaturall War: and the God of Truth, the preſident of your<note n="(a)" place="margin">This hath been anſwered before, and if an accuſation againſt us were enough who ſhould be guiltleſſe? If you think, Sir, you can yet bring any thing againſt our proceedings, which hath not been ſaid, and deſerves the name of any more then ſuch a cavill as this, you have your liberty.</note> 
               <hi>unexamined errors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, Almighty God, the Champion of his owne Truth; and maintainer of his own Cauſe, hath (to more then common ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration) appeared in this great Enterprize.</p>
            <p>He that delivered <hi>Iſraels handfull</hi> from the hand of <hi>Pharaohs Hoſt,</hi> hath ſhewed himſelfe in the (almoſt incredible) procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:159220:10"/> of this heaven diſpleaſing Warre; the briefe Relation whereof may move thoſe hearts, that are not ſeared, or ſtone, to melt into a thankfull acknowledgement of his Power, and remaine as Monuments of his Mercy, that children (yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born) may ſay hereafter, <hi>God was here,</hi> viz.</p>
            <p>The two Houſes of Parliament made firſt<note n="(b)" place="margin">That is to ſay, before the Papiſts could get them, for indeed they were deſign'd to have had them, that we might have had what they have in Germany, that is to ſay, neither houſe, home, nor habitation; <hi>The tender mercies of</hi> the <hi>wicked</hi> are cruelty, for this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therfore, and that ſeiſure, We humbly bleſſe the name of our good God. But good Sir, not firſt before the plot for bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of an Army againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Nor firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore many other things which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience hath not ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced among ſome of you, and in due time the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome will take notice of, Sir, with all your tricks and ambiguities, you dance in a Net, and your diſſimulation and prevari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation cannot be hid.</note> a generall ſeiſure of all the Armes, Ammunition, Caſtles, Forts, Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zines, and Ships, (being the whole viſible ſtrength of this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Kingdome) to whom (having now ſetled the Militia, both by Sea and Land, in their owne hands) tides of Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>gold</hi> came in upon the<note n="(c)" place="margin">Truely our gold came not in as it ought to have done; We had then, and yet have too many amongſt us whoſe earrings were laid by for an Idoll of their owne making. But now you ſpeak of our Incomes for the Warre; Remember I pray you Sir, that we do not forget ſome of your Receipts alſo. Firſt, The Lands and Money of almoſt all the Nobility and Gentry of the Land. Secondly, Malignant Merchants and Citizens, not a few. Thirdly, All the Civilians in the Kingdome, and (Reader) into their hands, all the treaſure of the Kingdome was running, out of all their Coſſers you expend. And indeed it muſt be ſo, for it was ill got, and muſt not be better ſpent. Fourthly, You received one ſumme from beyond Sea upon a good Pawne. Fifthly, And 100000 l. came in (they ſay) elſewhere that was holpen to be gotten by us, and now is ſpent to fight againſt us. Sixthly, All the wicked ones which are ſcummed off the three Kingdomes are on your ſide, theſe uſually love not any thing better than that which God hateth, and will give their firſt borne to a <hi>Moloch;</hi> The Gentleman obſerves it well, we are fain to ſtraine hard for monies, every thing expended in the things of God came too too hard But to Idolatry, every thing comes eaſie, the health, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.28. they cut themſelves with knives, &amp;c. the wealth, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.6. they pluck'd off a heir earrings the eaſe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.6: roſe early; their very children too. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.37. They offered their ſonnes and daughters to devils. Seventhly, All the Papiſts in Chriſtendome yeeld you their prayers and purſes, then I ſhall deſire thee (good Reader) to marke with me theſe two things. Firſt, who they are that fight againſt us, that is to ſay, a gracious Prince, and ſome others miſſed into the deep mire(alas) where now they ſticke ſo faſt that God onely can help them out. Secondly, what it is to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red theſe men will doe if they ſhould prevaile, <hi>viz.</hi> Pull downe any thing to ſet themſelves up againe, and to repaire the ruines of their (thus) ſpent ſtates and fortunes.</note> Publique Faith; Money (like blood from the Liver, conveyed through all the veines) iſſued to make a large ſupply, and where it ſtopt a while, mountains of maſſie Plate, from the vaſt Goblet to the ſlender Thimble, this faith removed into their ſafe poſſeſſion: And when the great Milch-cow began to ſlake, they preſt her nipples, and by hard ſtreyning renewed the ſtreame. As Phyſicians evacuate the Body, ſometimes by Vomit, ſometimes by Purge, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by Phlebotomy, ſometimes by Sweating, ſometimes Fluxing, ſometimes Diuretically, yet Purge but the ſame Peccant humour; So did they, firſt by Propoſition, then by way of Contribution, now by way of Loan, then by way of Subſidy, (no leſſe then 50 at one time) here by way of Aſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there by way of Twentieth part, then by way of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:159220:11"/> one while by way of Sequeſtration, then by way of Plunder, but ſtill the iſſue, Money: And to worke the better upon the affections of the Multitude, all this for the behoofe of King and Parliament, for the pretended defence of (God knowes what) Religion; inſomuch that men came in like Swarmes to the next Tree, or rather like treacherous Decoyes, with their innocent multitude into the Net, and Horſes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out number.</p>
            <p>Thus were they ſupplyed with all neceſſaries which the Arme of fleſh could provide, for the waging of an unconque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable warre, whereon the money already expended, makes no leſſe figures then 17 Millions Sterling, beſides the Revenues of the King, Queene, Prince, Duke of Yorke, and the whole eſtates of all ſuch as take up Armes againſt them, beſides free Quarter, and Souldiers yet unpaid. His Majeſtie on the other ſide, driven away with a few Attendants, not having among them ſo many Swords and Piſtols as theſe had Canons, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting both Money, Horſes, and Ammunition, onely what he received from the piety of ſome beleeving Subjects, (whoſe eares were Pamphlet-proofe againſt all defamations, and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals caſt upon ſacred Majeſty) finding ſlender Proviſion in his own Dominions; and that ſtopt or ſeized which came from forraigne parts: No Shipping, but what he purchaſt with the precious and extreame hazard of his few (but Valiant) Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: No Armes, but what he gained by the couragious ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of his owne neglected Life, the Subject of our continuall Prayers: Yet hath God covered his head in the day of battell, and bleſt him with ſuch ſucceſſe, that he is (by the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence) become a great<note n="(d)" place="margin">It is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of our ſouls, that his Majeſty were maſter of his own paſſions, and then of all the three kingdomes. And we do not doubt of both theſe, if God would once pleaſe to reſcue his ſacred Perſon out of your hands, in the mean time, we will not ceaſe to pray, that God would give him the great evidences of his exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall love to great ones, that is to ſay, a wealthy family, ſolid honour, and a ſure poſterity, yea, and that his ſoul may be bound in the bundle of life, with the Lord his God, while the ſoul of his, and our adverſaries be by God caſt out, as out of the middle of a ſling: Surely God is juſt, and the miſleaders houſes have been as the moth, or as the lodge, that the watchman maketh. <hi>Iob</hi> 27.18.</note> Maſter of the Field, and almoſt able to maintaine fight with his owne Ships at Sea.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The God of Heaven bleſſe him, and proſper him, and make his dayes as the dayes of Heaven, that being here the Faiths Defender, he may ſtill be defended by the object of that Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:159220:11"/>
            <p>Nor is the<note n="(e)" place="margin">To your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videntiall obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I ſay thus, Sir, Surely were not prophaneneſſe, and blaſphemyes as toyes, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles among you, you durſt not ſpeak, much leſſe print ſuch blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes as theſe, ſuch language, as indeed befits heathens, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then Chriſtians. Solomon ſaith <hi>Eccle.</hi> 9.2.3. That all things come alike to all, and the ſame conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (in regard of outward things) is to the juſt, as to the wicked: as is the good, ſo is the ſinner, he that ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, as he that feareth an oath. On all this, this Gentleman concludes preſently that, which <hi>Solomon</hi> gave his heart to know, and could not comprehend, <hi>verſe.</hi> 1. This Gentleman concludes, 1 That Maſter <hi>Hampden</hi> was puniſhed. 2 Thus, and in this manner. 3 For this, and this: Though you dare deal thus boldly, with the ſecrets of humane majeſty, yet if you preſume ſo with the divine, Look for your reward, and be ſure the damnation doth not ſleep of thoſe, which like bruit beaſts made to be taken and deſtroyed, ſpeak evill of things, and men they know not. But to the particulars (reader) the reproch which he would caſt upon that honourable man Maſter <hi>Hampden,</hi> hear the truth of: Maſter <hi>Hampden</hi> (as many other godly, and gallant patriots) ſtood againſt ſhipmoney, and ſuch things, as being (for ſo indeed they were) againſt law and liberty of the ſubject, denying to pay thoſe things which indeed ought not to have been demaunded: here-hence, a ſuite is commenced againſt the ſaid Maſter <hi>Hampden,</hi> a ſuite in his Majeſties name for the things aforeſaid, wherein he endeavoured legally to defend himſelf, and with himſelf, us, ours, and the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: chooſing rather to ſuffer impriſonment, &amp;c, then to do act, either againſt conſcience, within which is and wilbe, index, judex, carnifex, or law, without which ought to be to every good ſubject <hi>ſicut murus aheneus</hi> as a ſure defence. Sir, had his Majeſtie had about him ſuch as Maſter <hi>Hampden</hi> was, and would have pleaſed to have given eare unto them, (which we do not deſire to doubt his gracious diſpoſition in) he would have ſpoken to our Soveraigne words of truth, and ſoberneſſe, which would have been as ſo many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious preſervatives againſt precipices; but the Court was then, as it is now, full of peſtilent ſycophantiſme (more the pitty) wherein I beleeve your reader will allow you none of the leaſt ſhar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; Sir, I muſt tell you many bleſſe God for thoſe few, ſuch as this Gentleman was, and what aſperſion you caſt on him, you will never keep from recoyling in your owne face.</note> providentiall hand of God more viſible in <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpering</hi> him then in <hi>puniſhing</hi> his Enemies, whoſe ruines may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine as Sea-marks to us, and <hi>Pyramids</hi> of Gods Power, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a touch:</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John Hotham,</hi> then Governour of <hi>Hull,</hi> who firſt defyed and dared his Soveraigne to his face, what is become of him? How ſtands he a <hi>Marke</hi> betwixt two dangers, having nothing left him but guilt enough to make him capable of a deſperate Fortune?</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Hampden,</hi> that firſt waged Law, and then War againſt his own naturall Prince, hath not he (ſince theſe unhappy trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles began) bin firſt puniſhed with the loſſe of children; nay, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited to the third Generation, to the weakning (if not ruining) of his Family, and then with the loſſe of his own life, in the ſame place where he firſt took up Armes againſt his gracious Soveraigne? was it not remarkeable, that the Lord<note n="(f)" place="margin">The Lord <hi>Brooke</hi> is the next man you bark at, and he is dead, (more the pitty had it otherwiſe pleaſed our good God) had he lived he would have made an excellent inſtrument of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation indeed. But he tooke exception againſt that clauſe in the Litergy, <hi>From ſuddain death, good Lord deliver us;</hi> if he did ſo, it is anſwerable in the fathers language, <hi>Nulla ſubita mors piis,</hi> ſo Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> there is no ſodain death to the godly. I beleeve that noble Lord was better prepared for that which God was pleaſed to call him to, even that day he died, I mean death it ſelf, how ſudainly ſoever it might ſeem to you to come, then you ever were while you ſtudied the writing of this book; He that is a mortified, and yet mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying Chriſtian ſeeks to dye dayly, and deſires to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt, which is beſt. Thoſe that make their covenant with death, and their agreement with hell, whoſe only preparation for death is by endevouring to forget it, to theſe men death is the terrible of terribles, but the righteous is bold as a lyon, and is perſwaded that neither life nor death, &amp;c. ſhalbe able to ſeparate him from the love of God which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord. But he was ſlain out of a Cathedrall: Sir, I do not wonder that any friend of reformation ſhould be killed thence, they would kill reformation it ſelf, were it in their power: and this that you alledge, Sir, is one of the leaſt of their ſins: Alas the Biſhops, and the Cathedralls have killed thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of ſouls, here they killed the body indeed, but they could go no further, you ſet a Character upon that honored Lord, (though againſt your will) which will not be forgotten, and indeed the memory of the juſt muſt be bleſſed. You give him (as <hi>Caiaphas</hi>) an excellent <hi>Epitaph. Deo et Eccleſiae cecidit hic,</hi> My Lord <hi>Brooke</hi> fell for God, and the Church. And Biſhops are down already, what then ſhould the Cathedralls do up? Truly I do not know, unleſſe to be a neſt, and cage of all unclean birds, a harbour for dumbe dogs, proud prebends, <hi>non reſidentiaries,</hi> and a crew of ale-ſwilling ſinging men, who with their <hi>boatus ſtrenuus,</hi> loud lowing, (as that learned man calls it) ſing loud Abominations, morning, evening, and midday, where the counſells of God ſhould be opened to his people, and converts gathered in to our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. I have knowne that city, and Cathedrall, Sir, this many a year, and I beleeve there is not leſſe belonging to Michaels Church, Stow Church, the Chappell, and the Minſter, then 5000 l. per annum. And for the ſpace of theſe 40 yeares there hath hardly been a preaching Miniſter in three of thoſe foure Churches, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons twice on the Lords day in any one. Michaels, and Stow were for the moſt part not uſed at all, ſaving for their buriall places, There were one <hi>Maxfield,</hi> and one <hi>Maddox</hi> (blind readers both) ſtipendiaries ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively to three of theſe Churches, at I beleeve, not above twenty pound a yeare, and in <hi>Maxfields</hi> time the Clark (Iohn <hi>Bird</hi> by name) read the firſt leſſon, and gave the reſponſalls.</note> 
               <hi>Brooke</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:159220:12"/> who ſo often excepted againſt that clauſe in the Lyturgie, <hi>(From ſudden death good Lord deliver us)</hi> was ſlain ſo ſuddenly? who was ſo ſevere an enemy againſt Peace, ſhould periſh in the ſame Warre, he ſo encouraged? Who, ſo bitterly inveighed againſt Epiſcopall Government, ſhould be ſo ſhot dead out of a Cathedrall Church? who labouring to put out the left eye of eſtabliſht Government, his left eye and life were both put out together?</p>
            <p>How is Duke <hi>Hamilton</hi> (ſcarce warme in his new honour) taken in his own ſnare, having entangled his Lord and Maſter in ſo many inconveniencies?</p>
            <p>How is <hi>Holland,</hi> whoſe livelihood was created by his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns favours, branded with a double treachery, and like a Shit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlecocke fallen at the firſt returne, and ſcarce able to raiſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by a ſorry Declaration?</p>
            <p>Is not <hi>Briſtoll Fines</hi> (who at his Councell of Warre condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and executed innocent blood) himſelfe condemned (plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding innocence) at a Councell of Warre, from the mouth of his owne Generall, though finding (perchance) more Mercy then he either deſerved, or ſhewed? But that blood that cryed to him for Mercy, will cry to Heaven for vengeance.</p>
            <p>And are not many more ripe for the ſame Iudgement, whoſe notorious Crimes have branded them for their reſpective Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments?</p>
            <p>How many of thoſe<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <p>If you would name us ſome of theſe men, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, it would give much ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and make us to beleeve that you had not underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the impudent lying, which is gone out through the land: I pray you do not forget, Sir, what you are to make appear to us.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 That ours are blood preaching Miniſters.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 That ſome are dead, and many ſick of that bloody diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 And that if any one chaunced to be ſick or dye of a Plurifie, therefore (for this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man can tell) God ſmote him, becauſe he at any time ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to diſlike a peace even as bad (yet blindly ſought and ſued for) as the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ceſſation.</p>
               </note> blood-preaching Miniſters have
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:159220:12"/> died expectorating Blood, whilſt others at this time, labouring under the ſame Diſeaſe, can find no Art to promiſe a Recovery? All whom I leave to poſſible Repentance, and paſſe over.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cromwell,</hi> that profeſt Defacer of Churches (witneſſe <hi>Peter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough</hi> and <hi>Lincolne, &amp;c.</hi>)<note n="(h)" place="margin">Sure this Gentlemen was a Prebend, had ſome Colledge leaſe, or ſome ſuch thing hee's ſo zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dralls. But let us ſee for anſwer, 1 It is but if fame ſpeakes true, and <hi>Fama mendax, Aulicus</hi> will lye. 2 If the thing were ſo, as he ſayes, <hi>viz.</hi> watering the horſes at the font, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I do not know but that it may be eaſily anſwered, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity makes that lawfull ſome times which at other times is prohibited, Reade, Sir, and be not raſh, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.3.4. 3. Reader, thou ſeeſt the method theſe Malignants have in making Parliament proceedings odious, <hi>viz.</hi> O, they pull downe old Monuments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I beleeve wiſe men thinke that in <hi>Peterborough, Lincoln,</hi> and <hi>Canterbury</hi> too, there were many things were not fit to ſtand, or elſe they were in a better condition then many of their ſiſter Churches. Gentlemen of your ſtrain would rayle at <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, if he were now li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, for pulling down the good old Abbyes: But if you could ſee there are two moſt eſpeciall peeces of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence herein, 1 Blind zeal ſet them up, I am ſure, and you ſaid ſuch pulls them down againe: See God in this, here's a clear <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a very retail between the ſinne, and the puniſhment, Such zeal ſet 'em up, and ſuch zeal puld 'em down again. 2 Shall not theſe ſouldiers riſe up in judgement againſt many of our great <hi>Rabbins</hi> and Doctors, theſe droanes, and no conſcienc'd Seniors dayly ſaw, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> by, and cryed up this <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana,</hi> and will you hear the reaſon? By this craft we have our gain, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.25. Theſe that would be thought to be ſome great ones, came dayly themſelves (and cauſed others ſo to do) to offer neer the holy table (at my author reverently calls it) the blind whelps of an ignorant devotion in ſacrifice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of which ſacrifice I may ſay as the Apoſtle, The things which the heathen offer in ſacrifice to their Idols, they offer them to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills not to God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10 19.20. or as God himſelf of the them ſacrifices, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 66.3. At length come the ſouldiers in the ſpirit, (though not the wiſdom and authority) of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and they ſeeing this brazen ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent abuſed, break it all to peeces, and call it <hi>Nehuſhtan,</hi> you are angry, Sir, they care not for it: and for my part I muſt needs ſay <hi>Digitus Dei hic eſt,</hi> the finger of God is here. Some other things there are here, which I cannot paſſe over ſilently. 1 Your naming theſe Gentlemen ſo odly, <hi>Fines,</hi> that <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and plaine <hi>Sands, &amp;c.</hi> if you be a Clergy man I muſt tell you, In vain ſeems he to be religious which refrains not his tongue, <hi>Ian.</hi> 1.26. I pray you let us leave to be proud, the Lord hath pretty well begun to humble us, <hi>Ego et Rex meus,</hi> are ſtrains too high to hold long: This exalting of our ſelves above what is called God, and good, is a footſtep of <hi>Antichr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt,</hi> Brother amend this, I'le ſhew you your portion elſe, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.36. to cry out for a place in the Prieſthood, that you may eat a morſell of bread. 2 For the riſing of Monuments, was it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of coyn he rifled for? You ſpeak language as if there had been ſomething of gain there to be found: No ſurely there was nothing of that nature there. Vpon the ſepulchre of <hi>Semiramys,</hi> there was written, <hi>Si quis regum, &amp;c.</hi> If any King want money, in this tombe he ſhall find enough, that very tombe did <hi>Cyrus</hi> open, and there found an inſcription, <hi>Avare, tu, &amp;c.</hi> thou covetous fool, ſee here an Emblem of miſery, and Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality too, which ſhould make thee, if thou wer't wiſe, to regard no ſuch traſh. Then ſure it was for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence he did it: and if ſo, Sir, I will tell you, The Monuments of the dead had aſmuch need to be rifled, and look into almoſt, as the monſtroſityes of the living. A Church in <hi>London</hi> (and that no mean one) had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe 12 months as many braſſes (yet to be ſeen) taken off the ſtones as came to a great number, whereon is written ſuch inſcriptions as this; Of your charity pray for the ſouls of <hi>A. B.</hi> and <hi>C. D.</hi> his Wife, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upon whoſe ſouls, and all Chriſtian ſouls the Lord have mercy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Are theſe dead Poperyes ſit to ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eyes of living Proteſtants: and in a time of reformations? Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpies an altar, when time was, and at Athens too (I pray you marke that Vniverſityes, and Cathedralls too are not without their groſſe Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions) directed: <hi>To the unknown God, Act.</hi> 17. he cryes it down then, and if the Church had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, I doubt not but he would have pull'd it down too, and yet is blameleſſe; but if we do any thing the Kingdome muſt ring on't. The wolfe on a time looks over the hedg, and ſees the ſhepheard killing a lamb out of the flock for his food? Yea (ſaith he) he may do this, but if I ſhould do ſo, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> you can apply it. 3 We deſire you ſhould tell us where, when, and by whom any tortures were uſed on the tender breaſts of women; this takes I ſuppoſe like a ballot thats new among boyes, and ignorant people, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.2.3. <hi>Ziba</hi>'s lye, and the purpoſe thereof, I am ſure you know, <hi>viz.</hi> to ingratiate himſelf, by diſgracing a far honeſter man; Remember (Reader) and take heed. It was <hi>Davids</hi> ſin, his raſh credence, yea ſuch a ſin, as upon which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a worſe then that, the beſtowing of that upon a knave, which was the inheritance of an honeſt man, yea, and mark how faſt a lye ſticks, upon better information <hi>David</hi> mended it not. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.29. 4 That all our reformers need reforming, we agree with you, and it is our dayly ſuit at Graces throne, that it may be ſo with them: For if any cannot rule his own houſe, how ſhall he guide the Church of God. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. If then the reformers need reforming, what do the deformers do? if the cleaneſt places in <hi>England</hi> need waſhing, what do the foul holes, and filthy ſinks do. This hogſty Prelaticall hath been ſwept but twice ſince the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and the Temple at Ieruſalem had three ſweepings, in the three years of our Lords Miniſtery.</note> and Rifler of the Monuments
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:159220:13"/> of the dead, whoſe prophane Troopers (if Fame has not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got to ſpeak a Truth) watered their Horſes at the Font, and fed them at the Holy Table, that <hi>Cromwell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sands,</hi> whoſe ſacrilegious Troopers committed ſuch Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous inſolencies, with his (at leaſt connivence) in the Church of Canterbury, and uſed ſuch inhumane tortures on the tender breſts of women, to force confeſſion of their hidden goods, the golden ſubjects of their Robbery.</p>
            <p>What can the firſt expect, and what reward the other hath found, I neither Propheſie nor judge. If theſe, and ſuch as they, do fight for the Reformed Religion, God deliver every good man both from them, and it: <hi>Curſed be their wrath, for it is fierce, and their anger, for it is cruell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe (and of ſuch many) are they, that whilſt they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a Reformation, need firſt to be reformed.</p>
            <p>Nor do I, in tasking this Army of ſuch impious Barbariſmes, excuſe, or rather not condemne the other, wherof no queſtion, too great a number are as equally prophane; whilſt altogether make up one body of wickedneſſe, to bring a ruine on this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Kingdome; for whoſe impieties His Majeſty hath ſo often ſuffered.</p>
            <p>I but His Majeſties Army (beſides thoſe looſer ſorts of people) conſiſts of numerous Papiſts, the utter enemies of true Religion.</p>
            <p>To whom the King hath ſworne his Protection, from thoſe he may require aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>But, unto all his people, as well<note n="(i)" place="margin">Your Logick is juſt like your Divinity, Sir, I muſt be plain with you, an both ſtark naught, you ſay, To whom the King hath ſworn his protection, from thoſe he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire aſſiſtance. But unto the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts he hath ſworn Protection, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of the em he may requir aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. To your Minor. If you ſay, The King hath ſworn Protection to the Papiſts, ſo as to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants you ſpeak ignorantly; not ſo as to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, not ſo as to the Parliament. For the beſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are to have the beſt Protection <hi>Joſh.</hi> 9.9.27. <hi>Gibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onites</hi> they may be, if you will, but no more; and if the King of Iſrael ſhould have craved the help of the <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beonites</hi> againſt the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> ſure it had been prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous. 2 If you ſay, The King hath ſworn to protect them, every way, you ſpeak ſadly: And it is aſmuch as to ſay, The King hath ſworn to protect them, which if they grow ſtrong, and have not content, will powder, and poyſon him; You remember, and we too, the King of <hi>France,</hi> And I beleeve ſome of the aſſiſtants of his Majeſty that now is the ſon, their neer friends, ſhould have been the aſſaſſinates in the time of his Majeſty that then was King <hi>Iames</hi> his Royall Father. 3. If you ſay the King protects them other way, then by the Law, its no Protection but a toleration, like that of Vſury, &amp;c. in our Land; But the Papiſts themſelves renounce our Laws: The laſt Ieſuit that dyed, did (in my hearing) at the Gallows rail upon them all, he ſaid, They were bloody, ill made, and worſe kept, &amp;c. Then it muſt be Toleration, but that word will ſound ill. Nay fourthly, If you ſay the King protecteth, or that he ought to protect Papiſts any way, you ſpeak Illegally; for, Whom the Law protects not, the King either cannot, or ought not to protect, but the Law protects not Papiſts, therefore the King ought not to protect them. Whom the Law diſarms, of them the King ought not to require an armed aſſiſtance, and that againſt Parliament and Proteſtant par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but the Law diſarms Papiſts, therefore the King ought not to require an armed aſſiſtance of them. Again, I conſider his Majeſties Subjects, 1. As Men and Subjects, and ſo while they live amongſt us, doubtleſſe they have, and ought to have a kinde of protection, viz. 1. <hi>Quoad ſanguinem,</hi> as to blood, no man may kill them. 2. <hi>Quoad jus &amp; poſſeſſionem,</hi> no man may rob them. But, 2. If you look on them as enemies to Religion, and Papiſts, their portion is no more then, To be tributaries; To pay ſo much an hour ſleeping and waking; To hold themſelves in their <hi>Ubi,</hi> their place; To be uncapable of ſome offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and many other things, which other men of the Proteſtants have, &amp;c.</note> Papiſts as Proteſtants, he hath ſworn his Protection; therefore from all His Subjects as well Papiſts as Proteſtants, he may require aſſiſtance.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:159220:13"/>
            <p>Neither does he call in Papiſts, as Papiſts, to maintaine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion (as himſelfe hath often manifeſted) but as Subjects to ſubdue, or at leaſt qualifie Sedition.</p>
            <p>The aid of the Subject, is either in his perſon, or in his purſe, both are requirable to the ſervice of a Soveraigne.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">As to your caſe, Sir, I give you this anſwer, It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be but that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences will come, but woe unto them by whom they come; what neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity is there to uſe defence, where there is no oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh counſell tels His Majeſty, That they are againſt him, which are indeed moſt of all for him: And hereby he thinks himſelf ſtraitned, to call about him thoſe to help him, which indeed will neither help him nor you, longer then they think you help to help on their Deſigne, which is to ſet Antichriſt in his throne in England once again. The caſe then is this, Let His Majeſty pleaſe once to return to His great Counſell again, Let Delinquents ſtand upon their own legs, Let Papiſts betake themſelves to their Tribute, Reſtraint, &amp;c. And then ſee, Sir (if you be not willfully blinde) what neceſſity will be of this ſin, of calling in Papiſts, Rebels, Forreiners, &amp;c. As to your diſtinction, that they are called in, not to maintain Religion, &amp;c. Why? Your Religion, Sir, and that of Rome, will be enough conſiſtent. See <hi>Vertum: Roman:</hi> and you have the Ieſuits judgement in it, which I beleeve is of great authority with ſome of you. I tell you once again, That the Proteſtant Religion at large (and that's it which you would have) there went but a pair of Sheets between it and Popery, and ſuch a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion I beleeve the Rebels and Recuſants too will be eaſily perſwaded to maintain. As to that, that they are called in to ſubdue, or at leaſt to qualifie Sedition: Truly, you remember me of the trouble in Iſrael, in <hi>Abſaloms</hi> time, which when it was compoſed, and the people of the Land begin to differ among themſelves again, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.1, &amp;c. There was come thither one <hi>Sheba</hi> the ſon of <hi>Bichri,</hi> a man of <hi>Jemini,</hi> a wicked man, and he blew the Trumpet, &amp;c. and made a worſe ſedition then there was before: Beleeve it, Sir, theſe <hi>Sheba's</hi> that you have called in, when our diviſion is at the height, and their time is come, will be the firſt that will blow the Trumpet, and ſay, We have no part in <hi>David,</hi> &amp;c. we fought for the King, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we thought he would fight for the Pope, otherwiſe we cannot be for him, unleſſe he be againſt the power of Proteſtant Religion. As to our uſing of evil inſtruments, I give two things in anſwer, 1. Woe to that wicked Counſell which brings the good men of a Land into ſuch bad ſtraits. 2. I am perſwaded there are ſome, which put themſelves into the ſervice of the Parliament, and are wicked, that they may rob and ſteal, and do wickedly, and thereby (in the eyes of them which cannot ſee) aſperſe the Cauſe and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament-ſide. One Captain was hang'd not long ſince, who at his death confeſſed and profeſſed himſelf a Roman Catholick (I was a By-ſtander) and dyed for plunder.</note>Put caſe His Majeſtie ſhould uſe the aſſiſtance of none but Proteſtants; Tell me, would you not be apt to cavill that he is favourable to the Papiſts; neither willing to endanger their perſons, nor endamage their purſes; or, at leaſt, that they are reſerv'd for a laſt blow?</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:159220:14"/>
            <p>Or, in caſe Papiſts ſhould largely under-write to your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, ſend in Horſes, Armes, or other proviſions, would you not accept it, and for its ſake their perſons too?</p>
            <p>Are you ſo ſtrict in your Preparations, as to Catechize eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſouldier? Or, to examine, firſt, every Officers Religion? Or, having the proffer of a good Popiſh, or debaucht Commander, tell me, ſhould he be denied his Commiſſion?</p>
            <p>Remember Sir <hi>Arthur Aſhton,</hi> whom his Majeſtie entertains by your Example.</p>
            <p>Theſe things indifferently conſidered, it will manifeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that the honeſt-minded vulgar are meerly ſeduced, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the colour of piety, to be ſo impious, as by poyſoning every action of their lawfull Prince, to foſter their implicite Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion.</p>
            <p>But in caſe, your ſide ſhould proſper and prevaile, what then? would then our Miſeries be at an end? Reaſon tels us; No, God keeps us from the experience: Thinke you, that Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (whether new, or reformed) which is ſet up by the Sword, muſt not be maintained by the<note n="(l)" place="margin">As to the maintaining of the government by the ſword, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if ſo ſet up, it muſt be ſo preſerved, <hi>&amp;c</hi> I am ſorry to ſee That a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, a wiſe man (as you would make the world beleeve you are) ſhould wrap, and involve together ſo many, ſo groſſe, and ſo abſurd igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances; I will but aske you, and the men of your ſide theſe queſtions: 1 Is the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſts Church now to ſet down? Or the judgement to be executed upon his adverſaries, is it now to be written? See <hi>Pſa.</hi> 149.9. to execute on them the judgement written, &amp;c. ſee the places whereto all our expoſitours ſend us, as <hi>Deu.</hi> 7. And then I muſt tell you, you have told the world what a Divine, and Text-man you are. 2 Do we dream of our Power, or of an arm of fleſh, to maintain the Government of the Church of our Lord, once recovered out of the Divells hands? alas for you. 3 Dare we diſtruſt the Lords bleſſing, think you (we doing our utmoſt duty herein) both upon our King and us? You render your ſelf to me a meer carnall man: He who hath promiſed to be with us to the end of the world, To ſet his Kingdom in the midſt among his enemies, To tread down Satan ſhortly under our feet, To give a ſpirit of life to the two dead witneſſes, that great fear may come on them which ſee them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. Into his hands, and protection we commend our poore endevours, and let him do what ſeemeth him good.</note> ſword? And how can Peace and Plenty be conſiſtent with perpetuall Garriſons, which muſt be maintained with a perpetuall charge; beſides the continuall excurſions, and conniv'd-at injuries committed by Souldiers, judge you?</p>
            <p>Or, put the caſe, this neceſſary Conſequence could be avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, think you the ambition of ſome new States-men accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſuch Arbitrary, and neceſſitated power, on the one ſide, and the remaining loyalty of his Majeſties diſ-inherited Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, watching all opportunities to right their injur'd Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, and themſelves, on the other ſide, would not raiſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall tempeſts in this Kingdome?</p>
            <p>Or, if ſuch an (almoſt) unpreventible evill ſhould not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, think you ſuch ſwarms of Sectaries ſweat for nothing? Are
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:159220:14"/> their<note n="(m)" place="margin">You ſpeak; ignorantly and poorly, ſo you think, and write; Sectaries purſes? Alas Sir, God help our Treaſuries, if wee ſpent out of their Coffers: Theſe are the men hinder us, you are deceived. There is about London one (and I beleeve he is not alone) Ieſuite, in the Sect of the Anabaptiſts, He labours, ſweats, confers, preaches, defends that point with all his might, And why? becauſe he knowes that all the Diſciples he gets into that way, are all cleerly withdrawn from the Parliament: Their Tenent is, you know (if you know any thing) that Chriſt can defend his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome without war, and their uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all quotation that of our Saviour to <hi>Peter,</hi> He that takes the ſword ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh thereby.</note> purſes ſo apt to bleed to no end? Will not their coſts, and paines expect, at leaſt a congratulatory connivence in the freedome of their conſciences? Or, will their ſwords, now in the ſtrong poſſeſſion of ſo great a multitude, know the way into their quiet Scabbards, without the expected Liberty of their Religions? And, can that Liberty produce any thing but an eſtabliſht Diſorder? And is not diſorder the mother of Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie? and that of Ruine?</p>
            <p>Open then your eyes, cloſed with craſſe, and wilfull blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and conſider, and prevent that, which your continued Diſobedience will unavoydably repent too late.</p>
            <p>But, the truth is, They are all Papiſts, by your Brand; that comply not in this action with you: Admit it were ſo; Are not Papiſts as tolerable for his Majeſtie, as Anabaptiſts, Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, Separatiſts, Atheiſts, Antinomians, Turkes, and indeed all Religions and Factions, nay, Papiſts too, for his Subjects? Theſe of his Majeſties ſide come freely, out of their Allegeance, as Subjects: Yours are preached in, comming out of obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, as Rebels: They at their owne charges proportionable to their Abilities; Theſe like <hi>Judas,</hi> ſelling their Soveraignes Blood for ill-paid wages: Yet, both ſides pretend a Quarrell for the true Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>Good God! What a monſtrous Religion is this, that ſeeks protection from the Implacable oppoſition of her two Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions!</p>
            <p>His Majeſty proteſts to maintaine it: The two Houſes Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to maintaine it: O, for an <hi>Oedipus</hi> to read this Riddle!</p>
            <p>His Majeſty addes one Clauſe more: wherein if the other Party would agree, the worke will be at an end, which is:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>According to the eſtabliſht Conſtitutions,</hi> by Oath<note n="(n)" place="margin">You may bluſh to mention ſuch a word, was it not enough for your ſelves to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare, lie, &amp;c. But you muſt ſeek to be guilty of other mens ſins alſo? your oath <hi>Et cetera,</hi> was it not a fine one? And that I may ſay no more, <hi>borreſco referens,</hi> God is (to the everlaſting ſhame of that party) now ſhewing what the head of that faction durſt do, and did do, in the great Oath you mention, of which the world will ere long receive enough of ſatisfaction in his condemnation, and the truths vindication.</note> taken by him at his Coronation; And there the two Houſes leave him contending for a yet undetermined Alteration.</p>
            <p>And, for my part, I dare not conceive ſuch evill of the Lords Annointed, and my gracious Soveraigne, as to fear him perjured.</p>
            <p>Hath not his Majeſty, in the preſence of that God, by whom he raignes, imprecated the Curſe of Heaven on him and his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:159220:15"/> Royall Poſterity, (<hi>Sub Sigillo ſacrament.</hi> too) if He, to his ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, maintaine not the true Proteſtant Religion exerciſed in that bleſſed Queenes dayes, and propagated by the blood of ſo many glorious Martyrs (at which time God bleſt this Iſland in ſo high a meaſure) if he preſerve not the juſt Priviledges of Parliament, and the Liberty of the Subject?</p>
            <p>Nay, more, did not His Majeſty ſo promiſe the ſevere execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Statute againſt all Recuſants, that if he failed, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired not the aide of his good Subjects?</p>
            <p>What inferiour perſon would not thinke his Reputation wronged, not to take up confidence upon ſuch terrible termes? What notorious evill hath his Majeſty perpetrated to quench the ſparkles of a Common Charity?</p>
            <p>Conſider, O, Conſider; He acts his part before the King of Kings, whoſe eye is more eſpecially upon Him; He acts his part before his fellow Princes, to whom he hath declared this his Imprecation; He acts his part before his Subjects, whoſe ſtricter hand weighs his pious words with too unequall Balan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>Were he the acknowledger of no God, yet the Princes of the earth, (if guilty of ſuch a Perjury) would abhorre him. Or, were all the Princes of the earth, blind, deafe, or partiall, would not he think his Crown a burthen to be worne upon his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured brow before his own abuſed people? Or, (having renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced his Subjects aide, upon his faile) could he expect that loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, which now he wants upon a meer ſuſpition?</p>
            <p>But: He is a Prince,<note n="(o)" place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is our dread Soveragin, never the better (I muſt tell you, Sir) for ſuch as your commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if the old rule be true which is <hi>A pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>verſis vitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perari decorum eſt.</hi> It is ill to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended of wicked men: We deſire that our King may be inferiour to none of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly graces, no not <hi>Ioſiah, Hezekiah,</hi> To none of the Kings of <hi>England</hi> in earthly glory, no not <hi>Henry</hi> the 7. in riches, nor <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. in works of reformation, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill counſells that are about him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken from his throne, we doubt nor the proſperity thereof. The pulling of feathers from our garments to make pillows, and put under the elbows, is both the work, and emblem of a paraſite, There were certain fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes in <hi>Africa</hi> (ſaith my author) which if they did but only commend trees, beaſts, or children for the moſt part they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did thrive after it, <hi>Gell. lib.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. God bleſſe his Majeſtie, and his from amongſt ill tongues.</note> whom God hath crowned with graces above his fellowes, A Prince, whom, for his Piety, few Ages could parallel.</p>
            <p>What Vices of the times have branded his Repute? His Youth, high diet, ſtrength of body, and Soveraigne Power might have enclined, and warpt him to luxurious vanity, as wel as other Monarchs, whoſe effeminacies have enerved the ſtrength of their declining Kingdomes; How many would have held it a Preferment, to be Atturney to his Royall Luſt, or Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary to his Boſome Sinne? Yet, he remaines a preſident of unblemiſht Chaſtity.</p>
            <p>He might have pleaſed and pampered up his wanton Palate with the choice of Curious wives, to lighten Cares which wait upon the Regall Diademe; Yet, he continues the patterne of a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:159220:15"/> chaſte Sobriety: He might have magnified his Mercy, and ſold his Juſtice, to reward a Service, in pardoning offences (commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by thoſe of neare relation) yet He abides the example of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exorable Juſtice.</p>
            <p>Theſe and many other eminent Graces, and illuſtrious Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues can claime no Birth from Fleſh and blood; eſpecially, in thoſe, whoſe pupillages are ſtrangers to Correction; Nor, is it ſafe Divinity, to acknowledge ſuch high Gifts, from any hand, but Heaven.</p>
            <p>Which, being ſo, my Conſcience, and Religion tels me, that Almighty God, (who is all perfection) will not leave a worke ſo forward ſo imperfect; but, will, from day to day, ſtill adde and adde to his tranſcendent Vertues, till he appeare the Glory of the World; and after many yeares be crowned in the World of Glory.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Martial. lib. 8. Ep. 66.</bibl>
                  <p>Rerum prima ſalus, &amp; una Caeſar.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Phil. 3.8.</bibl>
                  <p>Rerum prima ſalus, &amp; una Chriſtus.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:159220:16"/>
            <head>Poſt-ſcript to the Reader.</head>
            <p>NOw thou haſt heard the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Reader, thou haſt read theſe notes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable peece, as they are pleaſed to ſtile it, I appeale to thee, whether this be not Scripture full of corruption and language, which is nothing but Sophiſtry: do not forget that the Devill quotes Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but our Saviour cites it right, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.3, 4. &amp;c. He is the Iew that is one inwardly, Rom. 2.29. And, not he that praiſeth himſelfe is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, but he whom the Lord praiſeth, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.18.</note> Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Scriptures, without Corruption; and the Language of Reaſon, without So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt not only heard Divine<note n="(b)" place="margin">The Precepts and Examples too, how impertinent thou haſt ſeene Reader, before, be not cozened with a blind confidence; Remember <hi>Solomons</hi> rule, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.15. <hi>The foole beleeves every thing, but the prudent will conſider his ſteps.</hi>
               </note> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, but thoſe Precepts backt with holy Examples: Neither thoſe out of the Old Teſtament alone, but likewiſe out of the New. Being now no Matter left for thy Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, prevaricate no longer with thy own ſoule: And, in the fear of God, I now adjure thee once againe, as thou wilt anſwer before the Tribunall at the dreadfull and terrible day; that thou faithfully examine, and pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the plain Texts which thou haſt read, and yeelding due obedience to them, ſtop thine eares againſt all ſiniſter expoſitions;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:159220:16"/> and remember, that hiſtoricall<note n="(c)" place="margin">Your rule for the expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is a fine one, are you not aſham'd of it?</note> Scripture will admit no allegoricall interpretations. If any thing in this Treatiſe, ſhall deſerve thy<note n="(d)" place="margin">Your an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer you have had plainly, Sir, by direct Scripture, and thoſe your own too, delivered from the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent perverting, as is to ſee to all men, not wilfully blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Now therefore I retort your admiration, and what you ſay to the Reader, I ſay to you, As you will anſwer before Gods Tribunall, be not aſhamed to vomit up your poyſon you have given and taken, and receive this Antidote, <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.33. <hi>If a man ſhall open a well, or dig a pit, and not cover it againe, the owner of the pit, &amp;c.</hi> Read and apply with trembling; There was a Bird in thoſe Countries, named <hi>Iuſtus,</hi> becauſe ſhe alwayes hid her Excrements, which ſhee knew to be exceeding hurtfull to men, <hi>Phot. in Biblio.</hi> I would you would get a Paddle and cover your dung.</note> Anſwer, do it punctually, briefly, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and with meekneſſe; If, by direct Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, thou canſt (without wreſtling) refute my Error, thou ſhalt reforme, and ſave thy Brother; If not, recant thine, and hold it no diſhonour to take that ſhame to thy ſelfe, which brings Glory to thy God.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 PET. 3.13.</bibl>
                  <p>Be alwayes ready to give an anſwer to every one that asketh you a reaſon, with meekneſſe and fear.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <closer>If the ſonnes of Sion get advantage hereby to eſtabliſh them in the preſent truth, I have enough; And let Chriſt the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords have honour in this; That great is truth and will prevaile.</closer>
            <closer>Deo Trin-uni gloria.</closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>There aroſe certaine of the Synagogue, which are called <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines,</hi> but they were not able to reſiſt the wiſdome of the Spirit by the which he ſpake, <bibl>Act. 6.9, 10.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
